<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-introduction">

	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		Disnix is a toolset used to perform distributed deployment tasks
		and is built on top of Nix; a package manager which has some distinct
		features compared to conventional package
		managers to make deployment safe and reliable.
	</para>

	<para>
		The purpose of Disnix is to manage the deployment of distributable application
		components (or <emphasis>services</emphasis>) in a network of machines. Application
		components can be anything ranging from web services, web applications, databases,
		and ordinary processes.
	</para>
	<para>
		Disnix, however, does not manage the deployment of the infrastructure itself and their
		system configurations. Normally, a system administrator must manually install machines in the network
		having the required characteristics by following the installation steps of the operating system.
		Moreover, a system administrator or developer must also manually write an infrastructure model, matching the
		actual configuration of the network in order to correctly deploy a service-oriented
		system, which may be a lot of work and error prone.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		This DisnixOS extension provides complementary infrastructure management tools for Disnix
		built on top of 
		<link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixos">NixOS</link>,
		a GNU/Linux distribution built around the Nix package manager. NixOS is a distribution
		in which complete system configurations can be built from declarative specifications and
		also allows atomic upgrades and rollbacks of complete system configurations.
	</para>
	
	<section>
		<title>Features</title>
		
		<simplesect>
			<title>Infrastructure deployment</title>
			<para>
				DisnixOS allows you to write a network of NixOS configurations in a model and
				to automatically deploy the system configurations in a network of machines through
				the Disnix interface.
			</para>
		</simplesect>
		
		<simplesect>
			<title>Infrastructure virtualisation</title>
			<para>
				DisnixOS uses the NixOS test driver to build a network of virtual machines
				closely matching the actual network and automatically deploys the service-oriented system
				in the virtual network,	so that it can be easily tested by developers.
			</para>
		</simplesect>
		
		<simplesect>
			<title>Automated testing of a service-oriented system</title>
			<para>
				DisnixOS uses the NixOS test driver techniques, used for the NixOS
				testsuite, to automatically script the deployment and testcases in a distributed
				environment, so that a service-oriented system can be automatically tested, and run on
				<link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/hydra">Hydra</link>,
				a continuous build and integration server built on top of Nix.
			</para>
		</simplesect>
		
		<simplesect>
			<title>Infrastructure instantiation and provisioning</title>
			<para>
				DisnixOS can also be used in combination with <link xlink:href="http://github.com/nixos/nixops">NixOps</link>,
				a tool that can deploy networks of NixOS configurations and automatically instantiate and provision
				virtual machines in an IaaS environment, such as Amazon EC2.
			</para>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
</chapter>
