<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-usage">

	<title>Usage</title>

        <para>
		DisnixOS offers some additional features to the basic Disnix toolset, which are shown in this section.
        </para>
        
	<section>
		<title>Deploying the infrastructure</title>
		<para>
			To deploy the NixOS configurations of machines in the network, the following instruction can be used:
		</para>
		
<screen>
$ disnixos-deploy-network network.nix
</screen>

	</section>
		
	<section>
		<title>Deploying the services and infrastructure at once</title>
		
		<para>
			In order to automatically deploy NixOS configurations in a network machines and the services of
			which a distributed system is composed, the following instruction can be used:
		</para>
		
<screen>
$ disnixos-env -s services.nix -n network.nix -d distribution.nix
</screen>
		
		<para>
			This command is essentially a combination of the <command>nixos-deploy-network</command> (which
			deploys the infrastructure and
			<command>disnix-env</command> (which deploys the services) commands.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Deploying a system in a virtual network</title>
		
		<para>
			You can also deploy a system in a network of virtual machines, which is useful for testing:
		</para>
		
<screen>
$ disnixos-vm-env -s services.nix -n network.nix -d distribution.nix
</screen>
		<para>
			The <command>disnixos-vm-env</command> command is almost similar to the <command>disnix-env</command> command,
			except that it generates and launches a network of virtual machine instances. Moreover, this command
			cannot be used to upgrade a system.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Generating an infrastructure model</title>
		
		<para>
			DisnixOS used a network model instead of an infrastructure model, which the basic Disnix toolset uses.
			Esentially, the semantics of these models are quite similar. The <command>disnixos-geninfra</command>
			can be used to generate an infrastructure model from the network model:
		</para>
		
<screen>
$ disnixos-geninfra network.nix
</screen>

		<para>
			The output of the tool is the path to the generated infrastructure model. This file can be used by tools in the
			basic Disnix toolset. For example:
		</para>
 
<screen>
$ disnix-collect-garbage $(disnixos-geninfra network.nix)
</screen>

		<para>
			The above command runs the Disnix garbage collector on machines defined in the network model.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
